Curriculum Vitae

Biodata



Ricardo Jorge de Araújo Ferreira

Electrical and Computer Science Engineer (M.Sc.) Student of Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering

Rua Conde de Ferreira 97, 4°D 4580 - 407 Paredes Paredes, Portugal

 \square +351 91 615 15 65

January 19, 1985

✓ ricarraf@gmail.com 7 /ricardojaferreira

in /RicardoAraujoFerreira

Summary

I obtained my master degree in Electrical and Computer science Engineering at the Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto, Portugal in 2008. My master thesis was in the field of Power electronics, control drives and measurement techniques, resulting in a group of power converters to be used in a solar Electric

Since then I have been trying to acquire experience and pursuing challenging job opportunities. For 3,5 years I have worked at Efacec, SA, as a control/automation engineer. At first my main activity was the development of automation and telecontrol solutions for electric power systems. When I acquired more experience I have started training new employees and to manage engineering projects, coordinate teams, allocate resources, supervising and find ways to improve processes and reduce the developing time.

When a new opportunity arose at the Institute for Systems and Computer Science of Porto to integrate the renewable energies team I took it. At this job, as a researcher in the field of power converters for electric vehicles and intelligent power grids, I have increased my technical and planning skills. I had also the opportunity to write scientific papers and to present them on international conferences. Being an R&D engineer was a great opportunity to go out of my comfort zone and to test new and challenging areas. During this job I found out that I really love to develop software.

I started to develop some tiny softwares to help on my everyday tasks, applications running on the web and locally, that perform data analysis, file creation and manipulation, integration with databases and others. And some applications just to learn and have fun.

Sometime later, I started to work has a developer and I am working on that area since then. I am currently working has a backend engineer in an Agile (scrum) environment with technologies like, Java, Scala, Spring, Kafka, Akka, MySql, Postgres, Apache Storm, Apache Cassandra, Zookeeper and several cache mechanisms among others.

To learn more about software development, algorithms and new programming languages, I have enrolled on the Master Degree in Informatics and Computing Engineering at Faculdade de Engenharia, a 5 year program and I am now finishing my final master thesis around evolutionary software architectures.

Work Experience

Backend Developer

Dec 2019 - Present

Blip - Paddy Power Betfair & FanDuel - Flutter entertainment Plc

Porto, Portugal

- Write well-designed, testable and efficient code in JAVA and Scala;
- Deploy and maintain applications in continuous integration platform;
- Execute full software development life cycle in a microservices architecture that processes 135M transactions every 24h;
- Design and develop technical solutions or processes aligning requirements with stakeholders;

Web Engineer - Fullstack Developer

Feb 2018 - Dec 2019

Jumia - Porto Tech Center Porto, Portugal

- Development of software solutions using JAVA frameworks, Spring and Play;
- Database managament and design, (Postgres and Mysql);
- Technical Specification and development of business requirements and improvements;
- Development of solutions with a strong concern about clean code and architecture;
- Working in an environment with the DevOps culture;

Fullstack Developer

May 2014 - Feb 2018

Gravity Demand, Lda (E-Commerce)

Penafiel, Portugal

- Development and integration of software solutions, client/sever programming (JAVA, PHP, Javascript, SQL, CSS, HTML5);
- Integration with external services (REST and other API's);
- Technical specification, design and architecture;
- Management and coordination between work teams (Marketing, Design, Sales, Development).

R&D Engineer

Jan. 2012 - May. 2014

INESC, Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering

Porto, Portugal

- Research, testing and development of power converters for electric vehicles and power grids;
- Design of analog and digital feedback control systems (Software and hardware);
- Validate emerging concepts in Smart-Grids and Renewable Energy systems by developing electronic prototypes;
- Development of software for validating concepts and make complex computations (C++ and JAVA).

Control and Automation Engineer, Junior manager

Aug. 2008 - Jan. 2012

Efacec, Sistemas de Engenharia, SA

Maia, Portugal

- Development of control and automation architectures for the Portuguese electric power system (Distribution and Transport Substations - 15kW to 400kW);
- Commissioning and development of factory and site acceptance tests for electric power systems;
- Management and configuration of large IP based Networks and information systems based on UNIX platforms;

- Management of engineering projects (Planning Schedules and coordinate activities).

FEUP Project

FEUP, Porto

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

Sept. 2007 - Jan. 2008

- Teach how to organize and develop an engineering project.
- Led weekly course seminars.

Education

MsC in Informatics and Computation Engineering

Present

Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto

Porto, Portugal

- Currently at the 5th Year, completing my master thesis: A framework for driving evolutionary architectures
- Principal Subjects so far:
 - * Languages and Web Technologies; Computation Theory; Algorithms; Discreet Mathematics, Oriented Programming Languages, Operating Systems, Databases, Software Engineering, Formal tests in software, Software architectures

MsC in Electrical and Computers Engineering

2008

Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto

Porto, Portugal

- Major: Automation and Control Systems
- Specialization: Power and Industrial Electronics and Instrumentation
- Thesis: Solar Car. (Classified with 17 out of 20)

Languages

(Scale: 1 - Basic, 5 - Very Good)

Portuguese 5 (Mother Tongue)
Italian 5 (My Father is Italian)

English 5 (Obtained the international C1 Level)

Spanish 3

Skills

- Programming and Markup Languages
 - Expert: JAVA, Scala, CSS, HTML5, JSON, SQL, JavaScript, C/C++, LATEX
 - Intermediate: Python, PHP, XML
- Frameworks
 - Expert: Spring

- Intermediate: Play, Laravel, Zend, ReactJs
- Test and Debug
 - Junit, PHPunit, Xdebug, Cucumber, Gherkin
- Tools and Software
 - Expert: UNIX Shell, Docker, Akka, Apache Storm, Apache Cassandra, Prometheus, Grafana, MySQL/MariaDb, PostgreSQL, Apache 2, Magento, GIT, Jenkins
 - Intermediate: Couchbase, RabbitMQ, Nginx, Hazelcast, Memcached, Redis
- Operating Systems
 - Mac OS, Linux
- Social
 - People person, enjoys being challenged, hardworking, leadership, entrepreneurial, organized.

Zi a de fouge de Anaige Fannel